[Steve] Do you think there’s a spirit world?
> Oh I know there’s a spirit world.
>> No, I don’t believe in that.
> That’s sort of a weird question.
>> Hmm…Evil influence on an individual?
[Steve] Do you think there’s a spirit world
out here?
> Sure, yeah.
[Roy Fouch] Parapsychology is a branch of
psychology that really delves into abnormal
experiences.
[Steve] Do you think there is anything to
the idea that there’s a spirit world out
there?
> No.
[Steve] What’s the truth when it comes to
the spirit world? Do spirits really exist?
Are they active in the world today or is it
all just fantasy?
Stay tuned to Beyond Today as we answer the
question: “Is There a Spirit World?”
[Announcer] Join our host Steve Myers and
his guests, as they help you understand your
future on Beyond Today!
[Steve] The spirit world—some whole-heartedly
believe in it. Others think only the shallow-minded
could be taken in by the idea. Your Bible
says, it’s a fact. What do you think?
Let’s take a moment to consider if it’s
real. Many I spoke to on the street seem to
deny the possibility. Is there a spirit world?
> I’ve never really thought about that,
but...I don’t think so; no, I don’t.
>> Not really that I’ve seen. I really believe
that people make their own decisions and,
you know, if they go a bad way that’s sort
of on them.
> As far as evils spirits, and the whole idea
of Halloween, no.
[Steve] Do you think there is anything to
evil spirits?
> No I don’t.
[Steve] Okay, we may feel that way, but can
we really know if there’s truly a spirit
realm?
Some think that research and science can find
the answer. Well, is it possible for science
to tell us whether there’s a real spirit
world?
> If it can be done then I’m sure science
at some point will do it.
[Steve] Do you think science could detect
if there’s a spirit world?
>That would be cool if they could but, I don’t
know right now.
>> I consider myself pretty science-based
myself, but there are some things that we
haven’t quite explained yet. I’m not willing
to say there’s any specific god or spirit
or power but there is something out there
that we haven’t quite put a name on and
really nailed down just yet.
[Steve] When you get right down to it—science
isn’t the answer. Most scientists theorize
that we’re products of evolution. They’re
biased against anything that’s intangible.
One man I spoke with is an anthropologist.
Anthropology is the scientific study of human
societies and cultures and their development.
Here’s what he said:
> We in the sort of materialist scientific
age denigrate that sort of thing. The real
fact is, that science is the study of stuff
that you can measure and metaphysical stuff,
of course, you can’t measure.
[Steve] Science has little to say about things
that can't be seen under a microscope, through
a telescope or things that can't be examined
in a laboratory. It deals best with the physical
world, but science is highly skeptical at
best of anything dealing with the spirit realm.
Do you think there is a dimension there that
is real, even though science can’t detect
it?
> Oh indeed. Yeah, I do believe that, indeed.
Yeah. There’s lots of things that science
can’t measure and the problem that some
scientists have is that things that they can’t
measure they don’t believe is real, but
there’s lots and lots of evidence.
[Steve] What a valuable point! Even though
science can’t identify it, there is a spirit
dimension that’s real. Because they can’t
quantify it, they don’t believe it to be
true.
But, is there a source we can turn to—that
gives us trustworthy information about the
spirit world?
Yes. There is a reliable resource that describes
the unseen spirit realm without contradictions—and
in a logical, consistent manner.
It’s the Bible. Of all the books that deal
with the spirit world, only the Bible has
been shown throughout the centuries to be
dependable. It’s a dependable source of
information. So, if we’re to learn about
the spirit world, we’ve got to turn to the
truth of the Bible. Go to the source!
The Bible proclaims it was inspired by the
One who is over the entire spirit world—God
Himself! We’re told: “For by Him all things
were created that are in heaven and that are
on earth, visible and invisible (Colossians
1: 16, NKJ).
God’s Word is filled with references to
spirit beings that possess intelligence and
moral qualities. When it comes to the evil
spiritual forces, the Bible itself helps us
to stand strong against them.
There’s a great example of this that occurred
close to 2,000 years ago. The apostle Paul
visited the city of Ephesus and he preached
from the Bible about the truth of God and
the wicked spirit realm. The people who had
been using evil materials reacted to his message
by choosing to reject spiritual darkness.
The story is found in Acts 19: “Also, many
of those who had practiced magic brought their
books together and burned them in the sight
of all. And they counted up the value of them,
and it totaled fifty thousand pieces of silver.
So the word of the Lord grew mightily and
prevailed” (Acts 19:19-20).
Today, many might think that we’re much
too sophisticated now to be that superstitious
about an evil spirit world.
> I think people want to believe there’s
something higher than just this mortal plane
that we have.
>> It may be evil, but I don’t think it’s
a spirit. I think it’s just mentality of
man.
[Steve] But the Bible proclaims there is an
evil spirit realm. In fact, it calls the world
that we live in: “this present evil world”
(Galatians 1:4).
> I do think there is some greater force out
there but I’m not sure what it is.
>> It has a definite influence on you.
> If I believe in any kind of spiritual world
at all, it’s something that we all share.
[Steve] Do you think it’s possible that
unseen world can impact our thinking?
> Oh I believe so, very definitely. Yeah,
very definitely.
[Steve] The Word of God reveals it is a dominant
force that stands against the powers of evil.
Yet, most are unable to see and fall under
another power and its influence.
What is the source of spiritual blindness?
Well up next, we’ll discover what the Bible
says about this evil spirit world and what
you can do to overcome its influence.
But first, let me tell you about our revealing,
free study aid that can help you understand
the spirit influences on our world: Is There
Really a Devil?
Is there a being that wants you to believe
a lie? Could the disorder and chaos in our
world be connected to spiritual influence?
Have you been swayed to think that demons
are simply just myths?
Our free study guide, Is There Really a Devil?
will give you insight into these and many
other questions. The Bible speaks of the reality
of a dark spirit world. It reveals how someone
could be persuaded to follow hurtful, destructive
ways.
You’ll also discover how you can stand up
against deception through the very power of
God.
To order your personal, free copy of Is There
Really a Devil? call: 1-888-886-8632. That’s
1-888-886-8632. Or, you can read it on our
BeyondToday.tv website. Or, write to us at
the address shown on your screen throughout
the program [Beyond Today, PO Box 541027,
Cincinnati, OH 45254].
Many question the idea of a spirit realm impacting
our modern world. Is that primitive thinking
or a valid certainty?
Do you think there could be an unseen world
that could impact the way we think?
> I feel like there is some kind of something
out there, but I can’t describe it.
>> Then we don’t know why certain things
happen. We can’t explain everything.
> I’m a retired anthropologist and virtually
every culture acknowledges a spirit world.
[Steve] Do you think there could be anything
to an evil influence that would affect even
nations?
> That I don’t believe.
>> I’ve always kinda felt that there were
spirits of some kind, but whether or not that’s
true or if it’s just in my head, I have
no… I don’t think anybody knows, do they?
[Steve] Do you think it could go to the extent
that spirit influence could affect even nations?
> Yeah, certainly I believe that. Yeah, it
affects us all individually and of course
nations are just a bunch of individuals.
>> Whether we are influenced whether we have
a thought, where does that thought come from?
I don’t know.
[Steve] Well let’s think about that for
a moment. Can it be explained? Is it just
in our head? From where does it come? Could
a spirit entity really influence you?
To answer the question, we have to start at
the creation of the spirit world.
First, God tells us that He created angels
before the existence of the earth as spirit
beings who cannot die (Hebrews 1:7). They
are described in the Bible as good and righteous
angels who shouted for joy when they saw the
earth being created (Job 38:4-7).
Well, God made these holy angels to protect
and take care of people. Psalm 91:11 tells
us that God “shall give His angels charge
over you, to keep you in all your ways.”
You see, God gives us powerful angelic help
for our benefit. Now imagine that! They come
to the aid of humans in fulfilling God's plan
of salvation (Hebrews 1:14).
Now, let’s consider whether an evil spirit
entity can really influence you.
There could be other influences at certain
times as well?
> Yeah I think there are probably some evil
spirits as well as some very good spirits.
>> So we can, we really don’t know what
influences our decisions. It could be our
thought process, what’s in our heart, the
way we were raised. You notice a whole lot
of factors that go in. I just think that’s
a cop out when somebody say, “oh, the devil
made me do it.”
[Steve] People do bad things and it’s because
there’s a devil out there that’s impacting
people. I mean, what would you say if somebody
said that?
> That there could be. I don’t know for
sure, but there could be.
>> If there’s any kind of evil it’s just
sort of turning away from that idea that we
are all humans at the base of it.
[Steve] Is it simply people making bad choices?
Evil people choosing wrong?
The Bible describes it differently. It reveals
a dark realm.
Now we’ve already recognized that God created
the spirit world to be good. So how did the
dark side arise?
The Bible tells us that evil began with one
of those created angels called Lucifer. He
chose to rebel against God. This was the beginning
of wickedness and sin.
God Himself described what happened: “You
were the anointed cherub who covers; I established
you; you were on the holy mountain of God...You
were perfect in your ways from the day you
were created, till iniquity was found in you...You
became filled with violence within, and you
sinned...Your heart was lifted up because
of your beauty; you corrupted your wisdom
for the sake of your splendor...” (Ezekiel
28:14-17).
So God created angels with free will, given
the choice to choose between good and evil.
They were also capable of sin. But Lucifer
defied God along with other angels and he
was changed forever. He became Satan—the
“Adversary.” This was the origin of the
dark side of the spirit world. He is the great
liar “who deceives the whole world” (Revelation
12:9) and, along with his angels—now demons,
he’s an expert of disguise.
We’re warned not to be fooled. “For Satan
himself transforms himself into an angel of
light. Therefore it is no great thing if his
ministers also transform themselves into ministers
of righteousness, whose end will be according
to their works” (2 Corinthians 11:14-15).
Unfortunately, many are skeptical and just
don’t believe it. I’ve talked to so many
people lately that have told me that Satan
doesn’t exist. Demons—they’re pure fantasy
and there is no spirit world.
But wait, Satan is no mere metaphor. Here’s
just how serious it is: “For we do not wrestle
against flesh and blood, but against principalities,
against powers, against the rulers of the
darkness of this age, against spiritual hosts
of wickedness” (Ephesians 6:12).
So, whether we’re aware of it or not, whether
we believe it or not; there is a great spiritual
battle going on.
What would you say to somebody that said,
“Well that must be evil that’s influencing
that”?
> It may be evil but I don’t think it’s
a spirit.
>> In every culture there are stories of evil,
right? And so they influence... there’s
a belief that something is influencing people.
[Steve] She’s right! God inspired the apostle
Paul to explain how Satan operates. He influences
people by transmitting invisible, powerful
negative attitudes: “... you once walked
according to the course of this world, according
to the prince of the power of the air, the
spirit who now works in the sons of disobedience…”
(Ephesians 2:1-3).
Have you ever noticed a struggle going on
in your own mind? You have positive and negative
attitudes, good and bad thoughts. And have
you ever felt them battle it out for dominance
to impact how you act?
Well the Bible reveals that Satan has that
power to impact our thinking. The devil has
the ability to broadcast destructive attitudes
as he tries to persuade us to do wrong. It’s
real. It’s dangerous. And it’s deadly.
Up next, I’ll speak with a clinical counselor
about this battle for our minds. Can Satan
read your mind and take control of you? We’ll
look at that in just a moment.
But first I’d like to remind you to order
our free Bible study aid, Is There Really
a Devil?
There’s just too much information on the
spirit realm and the part Satan plays to cover
on today’s program, so be sure to order
yours now.
Also, when you order our free study aid, Is
There Really a Devil? we’ll also send you
a subscription to our magazine, Beyond Today—free
of charge! Six times a year you’ll receive
articles on subjects that will not only help
change your life for the better, but help
you more fully comprehend current events in
relation to Bible prophecy. Our magazine will
also help you learn more about the biblically
sanctioned Holy Days; and about Satan’s
powerful deception occurring in the world
right now—and so much more!
So order your free copy of: Is There Really
a Devil? and our magazine, Beyond Today. Do
it by calling: 1-888-886-8632. That’s 1-888-886-8632.
Or, write to us at the address shown on your
screen. Of course, you can read Is There Really
a Devil? and Beyond Today online at BeyondToday.tv.
Here on Beyond Today we provide all of our
literature free of charge! This is made possible
through the generous support of the United
Church of God members and our many viewers
around the world. We welcome you to partner
with us so we can reach even more with the
genuine truth of the Bible. So write us today,
or go online to BeyondToday.tv. We look forward
to hearing from you.
Is there really a spirit world? Yes. And whether
or not you’re aware of it, a spiritual battle
is going on—a battle for our minds. So even
though we’re physical people, there’s
a supernatural conflict that’s happening
right now.
God’s Word tells us that: “...though we
live in the world we are not carrying on a
worldly war” (2 Corinthians 10:3, RSV).
It’s certainly not a physical conflict.
We’re reminded of the powerful forces that
we combat in our thoughts: “Keep your mind
clear, and be alert. Your opponent the devil
is prowling around like a roaring lion as
he looks for someone to devour” (1 Peter
5:8, GW).
I spoke with Dr. Roy Fouch, a Licensed Professional
Clinical Counselor about this spiritual warfare
and the impact of the spirit world upon our
thinking.
Now as a clinical counselor, do you believe
in a spirit world?
[Dr. Fouch] Oh yes, absolutely. First of all,
I believe in the Bible and what the Bible
has to say. And the Bible clearly says there
is a spirit world and that there are evil
spirit beings and that they do interact with
human beings. We see the effects of evil in
our culture today. So there is evil and the
Bible talks about it. And, we all are affected
by it in one way or another, if not directly.
But we also can open ourselves up to the influence
if we’re not doing the kind of things that
we need to do to counteract that part of the
spirit world.
[Steve] That is the challenge—counteracting
the dark influences that are all around us.
It begins with subtle suggestion and enticement.
An evil thought is introduced into our mind,
and if we don’t change our thinking, the
desire motivates us to pursue it. The apostle
James said it this way: “But each one is
tempted when he is drawn away by his own desires
and enticed. Then, when desire has conceived,
it gives birth to sin; and sin, when it is
full-grown, brings forth death” (James 1:14-15).
So we have to change the way we think.
Now unfortunately throughout the centuries,
many have confused mental illness with demonic
influence.
[Dr. Fouch] I’ve been working in the field
with the severely, mentally ill for 35 years.
These people suffer terrible lives in many
cases. It’s important to not necessarily
assume that they are being influenced by demons
or that they are possessed. That we treat
them as we would treat anybody who is suffering
from any condition. Throughout history people
have been confounded by what mental illness
is. And so, they’ve reacted to these individuals
as if they were demon possessed. They would
do things like bloodletting and drilling holes
in their heads to try to release the evil
spirits.
Thomas Aquinas, back in the 12th century,
a theologian, believed that it had to do with
demon possession or demon influence. And,
so what has happened through the course of
time, some of these beliefs have continued
down through the ages.
[Steve] We have to be careful about what we
assume. God’s Word teaches that evil forces
can potentially influence all of us. That’s
because Satan has the ability to transmit
attitudes and tempting thoughts from which
no one is immune.
Have you ever found yourself thinking an evil
thought and wondered, “Where did that come
from?” We’ve all heard the excuse, “The
devil made me do it!” But the truth is,
the devil can’t make you do anything. But
he can make something wrong—sound good—or
seem so appealing, that you’re willing to
choose to do it on your own. Maybe the saying
should be: “The devil tempted me to do it,
and I gave in.”
[Dr. Fouch] You don’t have to have a mental
illness to be influenced by demons. And I
do think that people who have mental illness
are much more vulnerable to those influences
because they don’t seem to have much control
over the thoughts that come into their mind.
[Steve] Do you think it would be fair to say
that it’s not always chemical imbalances.
That there actually is something for some
that is an effect of the spirit world?
[Dr. Fouch] Oh, absolutely. Not only people
with mental illness, but other people. So
we can actually open that door ourselves by
some of the choices that we make.
[Steve] Have you thought about some of the
ways that we open up ourselves to potential
influences? Is there a door in your life that
you’re leaving open? Remember, it’s about
your mind.
[Dr. Fouch] I believe that when you talk about
ghosts, and things of that nature, and witches,
and things along those lines—things around
the occult, witchcraft, things like that—you’re
definitely delving into the darker, spiritual
world. And, these things are presented in
such an attractive way, that our children
are drawn to them and we encourage our children
to be drawn to them. And these are things
that are part of the demonic world. It’s
part of the darker side of spirituality and
what Satan tries to do in my mind, is to sort
of dress it up—make it looks like it’s
fun, make it looks like it’s okay. And yet,
there are off shoots of this. So when you
start going in that direction, then you are
definitely opening yourself up to demonic
influences. The more you access and interact
with the spirit world on the dark side, the
more chance there is that something could
get terribly out of control.
[Steve] But remember, it’s not just about
ghosts and witches and the occult. The Bible
leaves no doubt that Jesus believed that the
devil and demons exist and that they have
evil influence in and over human beings.
Christ knew that these powers of darkness
are terrible forces of evil. No wonder He
spoke of them with intensity and with authority.
He didn’t hesitate to proclaim that evil
can be in our hearts and minds and it can
come from the very source of evil: Satan the
devil.
And so He warns us so we won’t be fooled.
It’s clear that: “The devil who rules
this world has blinded the minds of those
who do not believe” (2 Corinthians 4, NCV).
Now as strange as it may seem, he’s convinced
people that he doesn’t even exist and even
deceived the majority of people into false
religious worship. They’ve perverted the
knowledge of the One true God—even within
Christianity! Jesus taught us: Don’t underestimate
Satan and his demons.
But it doesn’t have to be that way. You
can protect yourself from the darkness around
you as you draw close to God.
[Dr. Fouch] If we’re going to be influenced
one way or the other, I believe, because I
think the spirit world does interact with
our physical realm. And so, if we’re focused
on connecting with the positive side—as
a Christian that would be connecting with
Jesus Christ, connecting with God the Father,
trying to follow Their instructions of how
to become more like Them—that that will
protect us. And making sure that you are constantly
putting into your mind the things that God
talks about and thinks about. I think if we
have minds that are more in tune with God,
there is less chance for our minds to be in
tune with the dark side. If we are engaging
in sin on a regular basis—pornography, addictions,
drinking too much, doing things of that nature;
sinning—I think anyone is more vulnerable
to influence.
[Steve] You can be receptive and choose to
let those wrong thoughts penetrate your thinking
or you can choose to be different. All are
told to resist the dark forces of the spirit
realm and “let God transform you into a
new person by changing the way you think.
Then you will learn to know God’s will for
you, which is good and pleasing and perfect”
(Romans 12:2, NLT).
Changing our thinking starts with repentance
and asking God to forgive us and to give us
the strength to overcome.
So make the commitment today. Turn from the
darkness and ask God to help you build a strong
relationship with Him in the light.Â
Now you can discover much more about the spirit
world and how you should respond to it in
our free offers today:
Order the Bible study aid, Is There Really
a Devil? and our free magazine, Beyond Today.
Call us toll free: 1-888-886-8632 or go online
at BeyondToday.tv for your free copies, or,
write to us at the address on your screen.
[Steve] Hi, I’m Steve Myers. I’m the pastor
here at the United Church of God Cincinnati
East congregation. I’d like to welcome you
to come and join us on this great spiritual
journey. We have hundreds of congregations
around the United States and across the world.
Click on the “Congregations” tab to find
a church near you. We’re committed to growing
in our relationship with God the Father and
Jesus Christ as well as fellowshipping with
each other.
If you’re looking for a home that encourages
living what the Word of God really teaches,
you’ve found the right place! We’re a
family—a family of Bible believers committed
to following Jesus Christ in everything we
do. We’ve found God’s way is the best
way to live.
We’re happy that you’re looking into what
God is doing in our efforts to bring His message
to the world. God is certainly pleased that
you’re looking into knowing Him better.
And we’re here to help! We would love to
have you come and visit and worship with us.
We’re looking forward to meeting you soon!
Come and join us!
[Steve] Even though we can’t see it, the
spirit world is very real. We know that Jesus
battled the powers of darkness and He won.
We can, too. He sacrificed His life so that
we may live a life free from the spiritual
hosts of wickedness.
Now in this spiritual battle, let’s make
the choice to fight against anything and everything
that even hints of darkness.
With His help, we can turn away from evil
influence to our loving God and the truth
of His Word.
Thanks for joining me today, and don’t forget
our free offers. Be sure and tell your family
and friends about us. Tune in again next week
for another edition of Beyond Today and join
me in praying, “Thy Kingdom come.”
For Beyond Today I’m Steve Myers. Thanks
for watching.
[Announcer] For the free literature offered
on today’s program, go online to BeyondToday.tv.
Please join us again next week on Beyond Today!